yes sir welcome to episode 13 in my
endeavoring quest to find a way to get
the audio quality up to something that
YouTube considers to be acceptable today
what I want to do is talk about the
question of technological unemployment
and to see if we can actually make sense
of the question of whether or not this
time is different
it seems that for a very long time
several centuries at least
there has been a tension between one
perspective that technology is dangerous
and harmful in the specific sense that
it puts people out of work and another
perspective that technology is helpful
and generative in the specific sense
that it generates more wealth and that
the people who have put out of work when
their skills are rendered obsolete are
able to retrain and find new things to
do
broadly speaking while it is certainly
the case that for the specific
individuals who have put out of work and
put out a vocation the experience has
been unpleasant society as a whole has
figured out how to overcome the dire
prophecies and has consistently been
able to figure out a way to in fact
actually continually keep most of the
population more or less gainfully
employed for the past several hundred
years however we once again find
ourselves in a conversation about this
and what I'd like to consider is whether
or not this time is different and in
order to do that what I'd like to do is
first figure out how to pose the
question well and in order to get there
we're going to need to articulate at
least six different concepts
unfortunately they're very closely
related so it's not actually going to be
that hard so on the one hand what I
would propose is a chain of concepts
skills ability to learn and capacity to
increase your ability to learn these
were roughly similar to the classic
chain of velocity acceleration of
gherkin
six which is just say that the the
greater your ability to learn the more
skills you can learn in the same period
of time or the more difficult skills you
can learn in the same period of time and
the more your capacity to increase your
ability to learn this is the jerk
parallel the more you're able to change
your ability to learn in time so it's
the second derivative and then in
parallel on the technology side of the
equation I might put tools the capacity
to innovate and the capacity to increase
your capacity to innovate and I'm going
to propose these are roughly equivalent
instead of marching in lockstep
so then given those concepts what I
would say is that first order what would
typically witness is a situation where a
tool is innovated and has the ability to
replace or obsolete some set of skills
and so the first thing is that a human
being
uses their learning their ability to
learn to learn skills and those skills
are valuable in their society and they
go out and generate value human society
uses its capacity to innovate to build
tools and as those tools have value one
of the things that they may do is they
may obsolete replace skills now one
thing to keep in mind is that this does
seem to be more or less a one-way
direction which is that tools replaced
skills and once they've done that those
skills are no longer meaningfully died
but at least not in the way that they
they used to be so for example the the
chainsaw more or less permanently
replaces the utility and the skill of
being able to use that kind of long
three or five men saw to cut down a big
tree having skillfulness in that
category is obsolete and generally the
way that society has responded to that
is by in fact expanding the scope of the
kinds of things for which one can be
skillful so to use a historical example
let's say for
someone had skillfulness in harvesting
wheat and then the automated wheat
harvester comes along the obsoletes that
skill that having that skill is no
longer valuable and and yet what ends up
happening is that there emerges a new
space for skills a new opportunity to be
skillful which might be for example in
repairing farm machinery which it exists
before farm machinery existed so the
human being that applies their capacity
to learn to this new space of possible
skillfulness develops the skills and
then now has a new valuable skill so
this is essentially the dynamic we have
a dynamic where you have a space of
possible skillfulness you have a
capacity to learn which relates to that
space which is the degree to which one
can then go into and actually acquire
and develop those skills in a timeframe
that is valid and then we have the
innovation which is the ability to
generate tools that expands and fills
the space of cost possible skillfulness
so sort of like a circle of possible
skillfulness and then a circle inside of
it which is the space of obsoleted
skillfulness that is being replaced by
tools
okay so first order the the conflict
appears to be at the conflict between
tools and skills but I think pretty
quickly we can recognize that the actual
conflict is higher in the stack that and
this is where we're beginning to get
into the real space of what's happening
now that for a very long period of time
human beings capacity to learn was much
much higher than society's capacity to
innovate which is to say that as this
the space of possibilities of skills
expanded individual human beings
capacity to learn meant that they could
come into and develop skillfulness at a
rate that was much faster than
technology than innovations ability to
fill that space so we've had kind of a
balance where once technology is
obsolete at a certain possibility of
skillfulness it's done but that as long
as the sphere of possibility of
skillfulness has been expanding
humanity's capacity to learn has enabled
human beings to learn adapt that new
possibility of skillfulness outside of
the sphere the advancing sphere of
technology and then remain in position
to being able to create value so then we
find ourselves faced with the principal
problematic and it comes from two
different directions one direction is
the question of what is the relationship
between the capacity to learn and the
capacity to innovate because now we can
talk about that second derivative which
is the capacity to increase your
capacity to learn and the capacity to
increase your capacity to innovate and
here's what we noticed the first major
problem human beings tend to be as so
far at least relatively limited in that
second order which is to say that
evolution has gifted us with a very
large ambient capacity to learn but it's
not quite clear exactly how much our
capacity to increase our capacity to
learn is it's there seems to be some
relatively narrow band that a
contemporary human being may in fact
have more or less the same capacity to
learn as a stone Age's human being we
have more to learn and we have more
skills and different skills to learn but
the capacity to learn may in fact not
have changed that much
by contrast the capacity to innovate
seems to be vastly more flexible and our
capacity to innovate seems to have
increased quite dramatically and so
while the relationship between capacity
innovative capacity to learn may have
for a very long period of time the grand
totality of all of history have been
decisively in the favor of human beings
we now may be reaching a crossover point
where the capacity to innovate is now
reaching and potentially exceeding the
capacity to learn and what we might
might think about is to think about
these circles there's the outside circle
is the expanding circumference of the
opportunity for stillness the kinds of
things that could be done the tad die
then there's a circle which is the
expanding ability to be skillful which
is the capacity to learn applied to
build skills among human beings and then
the inner circle is the expanding
generation of tools the innovation of
tools that replaces the human beings of
capacity and the relationship that I'm
focusing on right now is the rate
between circle 2 and circle 3 so circle
2 is expanding slower than circle 3 then
at some point circle 3 will in fact
reach and exceed circle 2 so that's
that's one dimension in and this is
fundamentally anchored in that second
derivative which is the capacity to
increase the capacity and so we can ask
some questions which is well what what
is the capacity to increase the capacity
of learning to what degree have we
explored that question how much do we
know about it what is it
right now already like are we doing a
good job at focusing our energies on
increasing the capacity to learn and
then secondarily to what degree is there
a way to apply the capacity to innovate
back on the capacity to learn so that
our machines are helping us overcome the
constraints of our machines I think the
answer to that is we don't really know
this is not something that we have a lot
of wisdom or deep experience in thus far
but at least we now understand what the
rate with the question is right it's not
obvious that the experience in the past
which was based upon the fact that the
relationship between that second circle
and the third circle was one where the
second circle had a higher capacity to
grow so long as the first circle
expanded the second circle had territory
into which to grow and had time to do it
before the center circle could reach up
and connect with it and the question the
present moment is is that relationship
it's the same or is our capacity to
innovate simply higher than our capacity
to learn is our capacity to increase our
capacity in to be simply higher than our
capacity to increase our capacity to
learn and if it is then for sure that
center circle is going to race out and
completely occupy the entire possibility
of skillfulness and there will be no
value in human skill
so that's that sort of that's that now
the other side of it which is also
interesting and it's kind of been the
subject of frankly the debate thus far
is the relationship between the first
circle and the second and third meeting
well what pace is there an increase in
the in the size of the possibility of
skillfulness so far we've been in a
situation where when we have removed a
particular volume skill like harvesting
wheat we have also generated in fact
generatively quite substantial at this
the circumference is increased in
therefore the surface area is increased
at a higher rate new possibilities so
that first circle has continued to
expand even as the third circle has
expanded but is there any principal
reason to believe that that will
continue to be the case
is there any literally any principal
reason to believe or understand how and
what the relationship is between the
expansion of tools and the possibility
of human skillfulness again I don't
think we know history has told us that
so far at least every time that we've
built new tools we have also built new
possibilities of human skills on us but
that's just history it may be that we're
reaching the end of that of that curve
for reasons that we don't actually
understand so I guess the point here is
that from my perspective we don't really
have any clarity on this question or at
least we don't have the ability to
generate answers with clarity but
hopefully this particular presentation
has at least made into well-formed
question and we can now potentially take
a closer look at the question and maybe
be in a position to actually make some
good choices around it